<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<knimeNode icon="python.png" type="Visualizer" xmlns="http://knime.org/node/v4.1"
	xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
	xsi:schemaLocation="http://knime.org/node/v4.1 http://knime.org/node/v4.1.xsd">
	<name>Python View</name>
	<shortDescription>
		Allows executing a Python script in a local Python environment.
	</shortDescription>
	<fullDescription>
		<intro>
			The node allows executing a Python script in a local Python 3 environment. The environment has to be
			configured under <i>File → Preferences → KNIME → Python</i> or via flow variable, as described in the
			<a href="https://docs.knime.com/latest/python_installation_guide/">KNIME Python Integration Guide</a>.
			Multiple input ports of various types can dynamically be added to the node and used in the
			script. See sections <i>Ports</i> and <i>Editor</i> below for a description of all available inputs, and how
			they can be accessed in the Python script.
			Make sure to set the <tt>knio.output_view</tt> variable to a view created with any of the <tt>knio.view</tt>
			functions.
			Furthermore, the node allows to import Jupyter notebooks as Python modules via the
			<a href="https://docs.knime.com/latest/python_installation_guide/#_load_jupyter_notebooks_from_knime">
			knime_jupyter</a> module that can be imported in the script.

			<p>The node brings significant performance improvements over the nodes of the legacy KNIME Python Integration
			and enables working with larger-than-memory data. More details on how to transition to the node's new
			scripting API can be found <a href="https://docs.knime.com/latest/python_installation_guide/">here</a>.
			There are also example workflows that further illustrate its use
			<a href="https://hub.knime.com/knime/spaces/Examples/latest/07_Scripting/03_Python/">here</a> as well as
			example templates on the <i>Templates</i> tab of the node.</p>

			<p><b>Please consider the following prerequisites before using this node:</b>
			<ul>
			<li>The packages <i>py4j</i> and <i>pyarrow</i>, are required to be installed in your Python
			3 environment in specific versions. We recommend to create a new Conda environment that contains these
			packages via File → Preferences → KNIME → Python.</li>
			<li><a href="https://www.knime.com/blog/improved-performance-with-new-table-backend">Columnar Backend</a>
			should be enabled for best performance.</li>
			</ul></p>
		</intro>
		<tab name="Script">
			<option name="Editor">
				The editor allows to configure the Python script that will later be run when this node is executed.
				In the script, use the <tt>knime.scripting.io</tt> module (imported as <tt>knio</tt> by default) to access the
				node's input data and populate its output view as described in the <i>Ports</i> and <i>Views</i> sections below. Use the
				<tt>knio.flow_variables</tt> dictionary to access input flow variables by name and to add new output
				flow variables by name.<br/>
				<br/>
				<i>Execute script</i> and <i>Execute selected lines</i> allow to execute the script, or selected parts
				of it, right in the dialog without having to execute the entire node. The outputs of an execution can be
				inspected via the workspace on the right side of the editor. Please note that all executions in the
				dialog share and reuse the same workspace. That is, outputs of previous executions are kept in the
				workspace where they are visible to later executions. You can use <i>Reset workspace</i> to clear the
				workspace before an execution if you want to make it independent of all previous executions. Executions
				of the entire node, outside of the dialog, are always independent of one another.<br/>
				<br/>
				The editor optionally provides autocomplete (by pressing Ctrl + Space) if the Python module
				<tt>jedi</tt> is installed in the Python environment used by the node (default if Python environment is created through KNIME).
			</option>
			<option name="Workspace">
				The pane on the right side of the editor panel is the workspace and lists the currently defined
				identifiers in the running Python instance. <i>Reset workspace</i> removes the outputs of all previous
				script executions.
			</option>
			<option name="Console">
				The console below the editor panel displays the standard output and standard error of the running Python
				instance as well as other information.
			</option>
		</tab>
		<tab name="Executable Selection">
			<option name="Conda environment propagation (Python 3)">
				Allows to choose whether to obtain the Python 3 executable from the KNIME Preferences or from flow
				variable.
				<ul>
					<li>Use KNIME preferences: use the Python 3 executable configured under File → Preferences →
					KNIME → Python to execute the node.</li>
					<li>Use Conda flow variable: use the Conda environment propagated by the selected Conda flow
					variable to execute the node. The propagated environment must be a Python 3 environment.</li>
				</ul>
			</option>
		</tab>
		<tab name="Templates">
			<option name="Create from editor...">
				Clicking on this button creates a new template based on the script in the editor panel of the Script
				tab.
			</option>
			<option name="Remove selected">
				Clicking on this button removes the selected template. Built-in templates cannot be removed.
			</option>
			<option name="Apply selected">
				Replaces the script in the editor panel of the Script tab by the selected template.
			</option>
		</tab>
		<tab name="Flow Variables">
			<option name="script">
				Controls the Python script executed by this node.
			</option>
			<option name="python3_command">
				Controls which Python 3 executable is employed by this node. The flow variable accepts the path to a
				Python executable, start script, or Conda environment as described in the
				<a href="https://docs.knime.com/latest/python_installation_guide/#configure_environments_per_node">
					KNIME Python Integration Installation Guide
				</a>.
			</option>
		</tab>
	</fullDescription>
	<ports>
		<dynInPort name="Pickled object" group-identifier="Input object (pickled)" insert-before="0">
			An input object. Input objects are automatically unpickled for you. You can access them via
			<tt>knio.input_objects</tt>. For example, the first input object can be accessed like this:
			<tt>knio.input_objects[0]</tt>.
		</dynInPort>
		<dynInPort name="Table" group-identifier="Input table" insert-before="0">
			An input table. You can access input tables via <tt>knio.input_tables</tt>. For example, the first input
			table can be accessed like this: <tt>knio.input_tables[0]</tt>. Each table is an instance of type
			<tt>knime.api.table.Table</tt>. Before being able to work with the table, you have to convert it into, for
			example, a <tt>pandas.DataFrame</tt> or a <tt>pyarrow.Table</tt>. Please refer to the
			<a href="https://docs.knime.com/latest/python_installation_guide/">KNIME Python Integration Guide</a> to
			learn how to do this, or take a look at one of the templates on the <i>Templates</i> tab of the node.
		</dynInPort>
		<dynOutPort name="Image" group-identifier="Output image" insert-before="0">
			An output image. The image can be populated via <tt>knio.output_images[0]</tt> in your script. To
			populate the output image, assign it a value like this <tt>knio.output_images[0] = &lt;value&gt;</tt>.
			The assigned value must be a bytes-like object encoding a PNG or SVG image.
			If no value is assinged to <tt>knio.output_images[0]</tt> the node will try to generate an SVG or PNG
			image from <tt>knio.output_view</tt>.
		</dynOutPort>
	</ports>
	<views>
		<view name="Output" index="0">
			The output view created by the Python script. Use <tt>knio.view(obj)</tt> function to create a view and
			assign to <tt>knio.output_view</tt>.
		</view>
		<view name="Standard output" index="1">
			The output sent by Python to its standard output during the execution of this node.
		</view>
		<view name="Error output" index="2">
			The output sent by Python to its error output during the execution of this node.
		</view>
	</views>
</knimeNode>
