<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE knimeNode PUBLIC "-//UNIKN//DTD KNIME Node 2.0//EN" "http://www.knime.org/Node.dtd">
<knimeNode icon="./pythonscript.png" type="Manipulator">
   <name>Python Script (DB) (legacy)</name>

   <shortDescription>
      Allows execution of a Python script in a local Python
      installation.
   </shortDescription>

   <fullDescription>
		<intro>
		   <p>
            <b>This node is part of the legacy database framework.</b>
            For more information on how to migrate to the new database framework see the
            <a href="https://docs.knime.com/latest/db_extension_guide/index.html#migration">migration section</a> of the 
            <a href="https://docs.knime.com/latest/db_extension_guide/index.html">database documentation</a>.
           </p>
           <p>
			Allows execution of a Python script in a local Python installation. 
			The path to the Python executable has to be configured in 
			Preferences → KNIME → Python. This node supports Python 2 and 3.
			It also allows to import Jupyter notebooks as Python modules via the
			knime_jupyter module that is part of the Python workspace.
		   </p>
		   <p>
			<b>NOTICE:</b>
	          The nodes uses the <a href="https://pypi.python.org/pypi/JayDeBeApi/">JayDeBeApi</a> library 
	          to establish a connection to the database via a JDBC connection which is included. However to use JayDeBeApi
	          <a href="http://jpype.sourceforge.net/">JPype</a> needs to be installed. For Windows precompiled
	          libraries can be downloaded from 
	          <a href="http://www.lfd.uci.edu/~gohlke/pythonlibs/#jpype">Unofficial Windows Binaries for Python Extension Packages</a>.
	       </p>
		</intro>
      <tab name="Script">
         <option name="Editor">
            The script in the editor panel in the center will be
            executed to
            generate this node's output.
            "Execute script" will execute the full
            script while "Execute
            selected lines"
            will only execute the currently
            selected part of the
            script.
            <br />
            <br />
            The editor optionally provides autocompletion (CTRL + Space)
            if the
            Python module
            <b>jedi</b>
            is installed.
         </option>
         <option name="Flow variables">
            The pane on the left side of the editor panel
            lists the available flow variables. A
            double click on a flow variable
            will insert the corresponding identifier at the current
            cursor
            position in the editor panel.
         </option>
         <option name="Workspace">
            The pane on the right side of the editor panel
            is the workspace and lists the currently defined identifiers in the
            running Python instance. "Reset workspace" will remove the
            output of
            all past script executions.
         </option>
         <option name="Console">
            The console under the editor panel displays standard output, standard
            error, or other information.
         </option>
      </tab>
      <tab name="Options">
         <option name="Row limit (dialog)">
            Unused in this node.
         </option>
         <option name="Use python version">
            Allows to choose the python version that should be used for
            executing the kernel. Available installations can be checked
            under Preferences → KNIME → Python.
         </option>
         <option name="Missing values (Int, Long)">
            By default, Int and Long columns containing
            missing values are
            converted to doubles in Python, because doubles
            are the
            only numeric type
            containing a built-in missing value
            representation (NaN). Converting longs to doubles, however,
            introduces imprecision. The
            conversion may be
            avoided by replacing
            missing values with so-called sentinel values. To convert missing
            values to
            sentinel values before script execution, check the first
            option, to convert sentinel values back to missing values after
            script execution, check the second option. To select a sentinel
            value, click on
            MIN_VAL (the smallest possible value for the
            column's
            data type),
            MAX_VAL (the largest possible
            value for the column's data
            type), or a manually enter an integer in the text field.
         </option>
         <option name="Rows per chunk">
            Large tables are broken into chunks when they are transferred between
            Python and Java. This option controls how many rows are
            included in
            each chunk. The default value is intended for tables containing few
            columns having numeric types. If larger data types like
            images or text
            are transferred, a single chunk may exceed the
            maximum allowed buffer size. In this case lowering the value of this
            parameter helps getting reasonably sized chunks.
         </option>
      </tab>
      <tab name="Templates">
         <option name="Create from editor...">
            Clicking on this button creates a new template based on the
            script in the editor panel of
            the script tab.
            <br />
            <br />
            Note: User defined templates can be found in the folder:
            <i>knime-workspace/.metadata/knime/sourcecode-templates/python-script</i>
         </option>
         <option name="Remove selected">
            Clicking on this button removes the selected template.
            <br />
            <br />
            Note: Templates provided by plugins cannot be removed.
         </option>
         <option name="Apply selected">
            Replaces the script in the editor panel of
            the script tab with the selected template.
         </option>
      </tab>
   </fullDescription>
   <ports>
      <inPort name="DB" index="0">
         An input database connection that provides all relevant
         information
         needed to connect to the database and an input SQL query used to
         initially fetch data from the database. In the Python script, it is
         available as DBUtil object under the name
         <i>db_util</i>
         .
      </inPort>
      <outPort name="DB" index="0">
         A database connection with the result table containing data
         from the
         database. The data in the result table is fetched either using the
         automatically defined output SQL query by the
         <i>db_util</i>
         or using
         the output SQL query defined by the user by executing the
         <i>db_util.set_output_query()</i>
         method.
      </outPort>
   </ports>
   <views>
      <view name="Standard output" index="0">
         The text sent by Python to the standard output, during the execution of
         this node.
      </view>
      <view name="Error output" index="1">
         The text sent by Python to the error output, during the execution of
         this node.
      </view>
   </views>
</knimeNode>
